Register of the John H. Bunzel papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Speeches and writings, 1949-2004
  - Political survey, 1996 (Folder 14: 22)
  - "Politics '96" pamphlet, 1996 (Folder 14: 23)
  - Clippings, 1997 (Folder 15: 1)
  - Engineer School Banquet, 1997 (Folder 15: 2)
  - Clippings, 1998 (Folder 15: 3)
  - Little River conferences, 1998-1999 (Folder 15: 4)
  - "Alumni Day Lecture", 1999 (Folder 15: 5)
  - "Alumni Reunion Lecture", 1999 (Folder 15: 6)
  - Alumni Reunion Weekend, "Politics 2000", 1999 (Folder 15: 7)
  - Clippings, 1999 (Folder 15: 8)
  - Little River Conference, 1999 (Folder 15: 9)
  - "Allan Brown Memorial," speech note cards, 2000 (Folder 15: 11)
  - Alumni Day, 2000 (Folder 15: 12)
  - Clippings, 2000 (Folder 15: 13)
  - "Dangerous List to the Right", 2001-2002 (Folder 15: 14)
    Includes correspondence with Joseph Lieberman
  - "Power, Politics, and Democracy", 2002 (Folder 15: 15)
  - Clippings, 2003 (Folder 15: 16)
  - Francis L. "Frank" Broderick Panel, 2003 (Folder 15: 17)
  - Clippings, 2004 (Folder 15: 18-19)
  - "On Becoming a Political Scientist", 2004 (Folder 15: 20)
- Professional activities file, 1946-2003
  Includes course material, correspondence, and printed material related to Bunzel's role as a professor, delegate to the Democratic National convention of 1968, and Hoover Institution fellow. Includes documentation of student radicalism and strike at San Francisco State University in 1968 and 1969.
  - Academic subject file
    - American political thought, 1955-1968 (Folder 15: 21)
    - Comparative government, executive-legislative relations, and Congress, 1953-1961 (Folder 15: 22)
    - Jacobson, notebooks, undated (Folder 16: 1)
    - Political parties, public opinion, and pressure groups, 1952-1957 (Folder 16: 2)
    - Political theory
      - General, 1948-1964 (Folder 16: 3)
      - Conservatism, 1949-1955 (Folder 16: 4)
      - Individualism, collectivism, freedom, 1948-1957 (Folder 16: 5)
      - Liberalism, 1946-1956 (Folder 16: 6)
        Includes writings by Bunzel
      - Socialism and Marxism, 1948-1951 (Folder 16: 7)
    - Power, 1946-1962 (Folder 16: 8)
      Includes syllabi of courses taught by Robert Lynd and graduate papers by Bunzel
    - Power (Contd.), 1946-1962 (Folder 17: 1)
  - Course material
    - Pol Sci 10: American Government, 1957-1964 (Folder 17: 2)
    - Pol Sci 140: Basic Issues in American National Government, 1963-1966 (Folder 17: 3)
    - Pol Sci 145, 1963-1967 (Folder 17: 4)
    - Pol Sci 151: Community Power and the Politics of Leadership, 1967-1969 (Folder 17: 5-7)
    - Pol Sci 164: Public Opinion and Behavior, 1951-1957 (Folder 18: 1)
    - Pol Sci 240, 1958-1967 (Folder 18: 2)
      Includes materials for Pol Sci 160, 163, and 248
    - Pol Sci 264, 1949-1962 (Folder 18: 3)
      Includes material for Pol Sci 164, 165, 261, and 317
    - Political science courses taught by others, 1962-1967 (Folder 18: 4)
    - Student papers, 1981 (Folder 18: 5)
  - Democratic National Convention, 1968 (Folder 18: 6)
  - Hoover Institution, 1993-2003 (Folder 19: 1)
  - San Francisco State University file
    Documents student unrest, protests, and a strike in the late 1960s
    - General, 1969 (Folder 19: 2-3)
    - Crisis file, 1965-1970 (Folder 19: 4-6)
    - Correspondence and clippings, 1962-1969 (Folder 19: 7-8)
- San Jose State University file, 1969-1978
  Documents Bunzel's role as president of San Jose State University through speeches and writings, correspondence, and clippings.
  - Clippings, 1978 (Folder 20: 1)
  - Clippings on resignation, 1978 (Folder 20: 2)
  - Farewell Roast, 1978 (Folder 20: 3-4)
  - Letters to Bunzel, 1978 (Folder 20: 5)
  - General, 1977-1978 (Folder 20: 6-7)
  - Information file, 1977-1978 (Folder 20: 8)
  - KNTV editorial, 1977 (Folder 20: 9)
  - Spartan Showcase, 1977 (Folder 20: 10)
  - Clippings, 1976-1977 (Folder 20: 11-12)
  - Speeches, 1976-1977 (Folder 21: 1)
  - Clippings, 1975 (Folder 21: 2)
  - Clippings and press releases, 1975-1976 (Folder 21: 3)
  - Speeches, 1975-1976 (Folder 21: 4)
  - Clippings, 1974 (Folder 21: 5)
  - Clippings and writings, 1974-1975 (Folder 21: 6-7)
  - Speeches, 1974-1975 (Folder 21: 8)
  - Clippings and writings, 1973-1974 (Folder 22: 1-2)
  - Speeches, 1973-1974 (Folder 22: 3)
  - Clippings, 1972-1973 (Folder 22: 4-5)
  - Commencement binder, 1972 (Folder 22: 6)
  - Flyer, 1972 (Folder 22: 7)
    Flyer listing complaints against Bunzel
  - Letters, 1972 (Folder 22: 8)
  - Speeches, 1972-1973 (Folder 22: 9)
  - Clippings, 1971 (Folder 23: 1)
  - Clippings and press releases, 1971-1972 (Folder 23: 2)
  - Event programs and invitations, 1971, undated (Folder 23: 3)
  - Inauguration certificates, 1971 (Folder 23: 4-6)
  - Photographs, 1971-1973, undated (Folder 23: 7)
  - Speeches, 1971-1972 (Folder 24: 1)
  - Certificates, 1970-1972 (Folder 24: 2)
  - Clippings, 1970-1971 (Folder 24: 3-4)
  - Letters and clippings, 1970-1978 (Folder 24: 5-6)
  - Letters of congratulations, 1970 (Folder 24: 7-9)
  - Letters of congratulations (Contd.), 1970 (Folder 25: 1-4)
  - Letter and press release, 1970 (Folder 25: 5)
    Letter most likely from Barbara Bunzel
  - Media memorabilia, 1970-1971 (Folder 25: 6)
  - Memoranda and letters, 1970-1973 (Folder 25: 7)
  - Miscellany, 1970, undated (Folder 25: 8)
  - Photographs, 1970, 2005 (Folder 25: 9)
  - Speeches, 1970-1971 (Folder 25: 10)
  - General, 1969-1981 (Folder 25: 11)
  - Fundraising advertisement, undated (Folder 25: 12)
  - Letters, undated (Folder 25: 13)
  - Photographs, undated (Folder 25: 14)
- Institute for Educational Affairs, 1976-1982
  Includes board meeting materials (agendas, minutes, grant proposals, and reports), informational materials, reports, and memoranda.
  - Address cards, undated (Folder 26: 1)
  - Background materials, 1980 (Folder 26: 2)
  - Board meetings
    - March 19, 1979 (Folder 26: 3)
    - June 22, 1979 (Folder 26: 4)
    - September 20, 1979 (Folder 26: 5)
    - January 14, 1980 (Folder 26: 6)
    - March 28, 1980 (Folder 26: 7)
    - July 18, 1980 (Folder 26: 8)
    - October 24, 1980 (Folder 26: 9)
    - January 23, 1981 (Folder 26: 10)
    - April 29, 1981 (Folder 26: 11)
    - July 10, 1981 (Folder 26: 12)
    - October 23, 1981 (Folder 27: 1)
    - February 5, 1982 (Folder 27: 2)
    - May 5, 1982 (Folder 27: 3)
  - Education reports
    - Education reform, undated (Folder 27: 4)
    - Project Longstep, 1976 (Folder 27: 5-7)
    - Project Longstep (Contd.), 1976 (Folder 28: 1)
  - Form letters and requests, undated (Folder 28: 2)
  - Grant application, circa 1980 (Folder 28: 3)
  - "Guide to Public Policy Research Organizations", 1980 (Folder 28: 4)
  - The I.E.A Report newsletter, 1980 (Folder 28: 5)
  - Memoranda, 1980 (Folder 28: 6)
  - Resolutions, undated (Folder 28: 7)
- United States Commission on Civil Rights, 1972-1987
  Includes meeting materials, memoranda, and consultation/hearing binders related to comparable worth, affirmative action, and fair housing.
  - General, 1981-1985 (Folder 28: 8)
  - Annual State Advisory Committee Chairperson's Conference transcripts, 1985 (Folder 28: 9-10)
  - Background pamphlet, undated (Folder 28: 11)
  - Bibliography on fair housing issues, 1986 (Folder 28: 12)
  - Catalog of publications, 1984 (Folder 28: 13)
  - Clearinghouse publications, 1984-1985 (Folder 29: 1)
  - Comparable worth report
    - Draft, undated (Folder 29: 2)
    - General Accounting Office comments, 1985 (Folder 29: 3)
  - Congressional hearing volumes on Equal Rights Amendment, 1985 (Folder 29: 4)
  - Consultation on Comparable Worth
    - Analysis and recommendations, 1985 (Folder 29: 5)
    - Panel binder, 1984 (Folder 30: 1-4)
    - Pros and cons binder, 1983-1984 (Folder 30: 5)
    - Pros and cons binder (Contd.), 1983-1984 (Folder 31: 1)
    - Proceedings, 1984 (Folder 31: 2-4)
  - Consultation/Hearing on Affirmative Action
    - General, undated (Folder 31: 5)
    - Panel binder, 1985 (Folder 31: 6)
    - Panel binder (Contd.), 1985 (Folder 32: 1)
    - Pros and cons binder, 1979-1984 (Folder 32: 2-4)
    - Papers, 1985 (Folder 32: 5-7)
    - Papers (Contd.), 1985 (Folder 33: 1-2)
    - Proceedings, 1985 (Folder 33: 3)
  - Consultation/Hearing on Issues in Housing Discrimination
    - Panel binder, 1985 (Folder 33: 4-6)
    - Panel binder (Contd.), 1985 (Folder 34: 1)
    - Papers, 1985 (Folder 34: 2)
  - Hearing on Enforcement of the Indian Civil Rights Act, 1986 (Folder 34: 3)
  - Hearing on the Protection of Handicapped Newborns, 1985 (Folder 34: 4-5)
  - Hearing on the Protection of Handicapped Newborns, 1986 (Folder 35: 1)
  - Meetings
    - July 1984 (Folder 35: 2-3)
    - May 1985 (Folder 35: 4)
    - June 1985 (Folder 35: 5)
    - July 1985 (Folder 35: 6)
    - October 1985 (Folder 36: 1-2)
  - Memoranda
    - 1984 (Folder 36: 3-4)
    - 1985 (Folder 36: 5-6)
    - 1985 (Contd.) (Folder 37: 1-7)
    - 1985 (Contd.) (Folder 38: 1-3)
    - 1986 (Folder 38: 4-7)
    - 1986 (Contd.) (Folder 39: 1-2)
  - New Perspectives, 1984-1986 (Folder 39: 3)
  - Printed matter, 1972, 1984-1986 (Folder 39: 4-7)
  - Reports
    - "Economic Progress of Black Men in America", 1986 (Folder 40: 1-5)
      Includes typescript, comments, correspondence, and memoranda
    - "The Economic Status of Americans of Eastern and Southern European Descent", undated (Folder 40: 6)
    - "A Technical Report on the Economic Status of Euroethnic Americans", 1986 (Folder 40: 7)
  - Resignation clippings, 1986 (Folder 40: 8)
  - School Desegregation Study pamphlet, undated (Folder 41: 1)
  - Subject file
    - Asian Americans, 1985-1986 (Folder 41: 2)
    - Brown v. Board of Education, 30 years later, 1972-1979 (Folder 41: 3)
    - Comparable worth, 1982-1986 (Folder 41: 4-7)
    - Comparable worth, 1982-1986 (Contd.) (Folder 42: 1-4)
    - Grove City and Title IX, 1984 (Folder 42: 5)
    - Labor Party, 1979-1986 (Folder 42: 6)
    - Pendleton, Clarence, 1985-1986 (Folder 42: 7-8)
    - Populist Party, 1984 (Folder 42: 9)
    - Religious exemption, 1985-1986 (Folder 42: 10)
    - School desegregation, 1979-1985 (Folder 43: 1)
    - Set-aside programs, 1979-1986 (Folder 43: 2-4)
  - Testimony and statements, 1983-1987 (Folder 43: 5)
    Includes statement of Bunzel and others titled "The Economic Progress of Black Men in America"
  - Transcript of comments on poverty, undated (Folder 43: 6)
  - Writings and memoranda of Bunzel, 1983-1984 (Folder 43: 7)
- Subject file, 1969-1984
  Includes clippings, printed matter, and notes on education and civil rights issues.
  - Academic and faculty government, 1970-1983 (Folder 43: 8)
  - Academic and faculty government, 1970-1983 (Contd.) (Folder 44: 1)
  - Dinnan, James case, 1980-1981 (Folder 44: 2-3)
  - Discrimination in lay offs, 1981-1982 (Folder 44: 4-5)
  - Faculty, 1969-1978 (Folder 44: 6)
  - Students, 1969-1979 (Folder 45: 1)
  - Tenure, 1970-1984 (Folder 45: 2-3)
  - Voting Rights Act, 1981-1982 (Folder 45: 4-7)
  - Voting Rights Act, 1981-1982 (Contd.) (Folder 46: 1-3)
- Audiovisual material, 1971-2003
  Contains compact sound cassettes, VHS tapes, and sound reels of Bunzel's speeches and events at San Jose State. Includes videotape of Bunzel being interviewed at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.
  - Compact sound cassettes
    - Untitled, undated (Folder 47: 1-2)
      Two compact sound cassettes
    - "Rescuing Equality", 2 February 1976 (Folder 47: 3)
    - Dr. Bunzel's roast at San Jose State University, 11 May 1978 (Folder 47: 4-7)
      Four compact sound cassettes
    - "A Conversation with San Jose State University President John Bunzel", 24 July 1978 (Folder 47: 8)
    - "Moral Dimensions Behind the Headlines" by William Lester, "Major Errors in Current Political Thinking," and "Affirmative Action", 25 June 1989 (Folder 47: 9)
    - "A Service of Remembrance: Sidney Hook," Hoover Institution, Stanford University, 18 July 1989 (Folder 47: 10)
    - "The Honorable John H. Bunzel," Commonwealth Club of California, 19 April 1991 (Folder 47: 11)
    - Introduction to [Hartfeld], KQED, 13 January 1992 (Folder 47: 12)
    - Speech by Bunzel at Memorial Auditorium, Stanford University, 1 October 1993 (Folder 47: 13)
    - "A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Farm," John H. Bunzel, 12 October 1995 (Folder 47: 14)
    - "A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Farm," John H. Bunzel, 10 October 1996 (Folder 47: 15-16)
    - San Jose Rotary, Dinkelspiel Auditorium, John Bunzel, 25 September 1997 (Folder 47: 17)
    - "Hilarity," Annenberg, October 2000 (Folder 47: 18)
    - "From Here to Hilarity", 18 October 2002 (Folder 47: 19)
    - "President Carl Cilker's Time," Rotary Club of San Jose meeting at Lou's Village and "Comedy and Music by Jack Bunzel and the Spartoons," introduced by Ray Silva, 9 April 2003 (Folder 47: 20)
  - VHS tapes
    - John Bunzel interview at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, 15 October 2003 (Folder 48: 1)
      Includes Bunzel's comment on Edward Teller
  - Sound reels
    - "President's Faculty Meeting", 12 February 1971 (Folder 48: 2)
    - John Bunzel's San Jose State inauguration and Max Cerner's commencement address, 4 June 1971 (Folder 48: 3)
- Oversize material and ephemera, 1969-1974
  Includes magazines and coffee mug imprinted with newspaper article about Bunzel.
  - Magazines, 1969, 1974 (Box 49)
    Includes "SJS's Jack Bunzel--Commitment to An Ivy Idea" in California Today, San Jose Mercury News Sunday Magazine
  - Coffee mug, circa 1973 (Box 49)
    Imprinted with San Jose Mercury News article titled "Jack Bunzel Knows the Way to San Jose"